Register of the Vrangel' family papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Vrangel' family papers
1849-2003
95012
Vrangel' family
9 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box 6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The Vrangel' family papers include correspondence, printed matter, and photographs, relating to Russian military activities during World War I, White Russian military activities during the Russian Civil War, and especially to Russian émigré affairs in the interwar period. Includes obituaries of Petr Vrangel' and letters of condolence following his death. Mainly in Russian.
Administrative Information
Access
Microfilm use only.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1995
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
A veteran of the Russian-Japanese War (1904-1905) and World War I General Baron Petr Nikolaevich Vrangel' joined the anti-Bolshevik armies in Southern Russia in late 1917. He was known for many years in Russia as the "black baron" and "the last enemy of the Soviet Republic", while on the other hand he was honored as "the last knight of the Russian Empire" by his comrades. Vrangel' was the commander-in-chief of the White Army in the final stage of the Civil War and leader of the White émigré movement.
After the rout in early 1920 of the Denikin forces, Vrangel' succeeded Denikin in command and soon whipped the demoralized remains of the White Army into shape. He also tried to win popular support with a program for land reform. Vrangel' was successful for a while on the Crimean front, but after the Russian armistice with Poland in October 1920, the Communists were able to concentrate larger forces against him. Vrangel' was forced back into the Crimea, and in November 1920, he had to evacuate his forces to Constantinople. The Russian Civil War thus came to an end. Vrangel' died in exile at Brussels. His children believed he had been poisoned by the Soviet secret police. He is buried in the Russian Cathedral in Belgrade.
This collection contains personal papers of the members of the Vrangel' family: General Baron Petr Nikolaevich Vrangel', his wife Baroness Ol'ga Mikhailovna Vrangel' (including papers relating to her grandfather, conservative Russian journalist Mikhail Katkov), their son Baron Alexis (Aleksei Petrovich) Vrangel', and grandson Baron Petr Petrovich Vrangel', as well as his mother Baroness Maria Dmitrievna Vrangel', his brother Baron Nikolai Nikolaevich Vrangel', and granddaughter Natal'ia.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Vrangel' family papers include correspondence, photographs, and military papers relating to Russian military activities during World War I, White Russian military activities during the Russian Civil War, and especially to Russian émigré affairs in the interwar period and after. They include obituaries of Petr Vrangel' and letters of condolence following his death. The materials are mainly in Russian.
This collection contains personal papers of the members of the Vrangel' family: Petr Nikolaevich Vrangel', his wife Ol'ga Mikhailovna Vrangel', their son Alexis (Aleksei Petrovich) Vrangel', and grandson Petr Petrovich Vrangel', as well as his mother Baroness Maria Dmitrievna Vrangel', his brother Nikolai Nikolaevich Vrangel', and granddaughter Natal'ia.
A significant part of the collection are the letters from Petr Nikolaevich Vrangel' to his wife Ol'ga during his time in the Army. The original correspondence was sent over an extensive time period; starting in pre-revolutionary times, through the Russian Revolution and Civil War period, and ending with the emigration. The letters give a unique picture of the dynamic situation in the Russian Army in exile with information on various people, military units and schools in emigration.
Baroness Olga Mikhailovna Vrangel' worked as a volunteer nurse with the Russian Army during World War I, and after the revolution headed a group of volunteers who organized a tuberculosis sanitarium in Belgrade, Yugoslavia. During the 1930s, while living in Belgium, she raised funds for the support and education of young Russian refugees. She later came to the United States, where she died in 1968. Olga Mikhailovna served as chairman of the Ladies Welfare Committee at Our Lady of Kazan Russian Orthodox Church in Long Island. Her papers include personal documents and correspondence.
The papers of Baron Alexis (Aleksei Petrovich) Vrangel' contain materials on their family genealogy, correspondence, and a memoirs relating to the Russian Civil War and his grandfather Petr Nikolaevich Vrangel'.
The increment received in 2009 contains material relating to conservative Russian journalist Mikhail Katkov, grandfather of Olga Vrangel.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four series: Family file, Photographs, Mlitary Archive, and Katkov Family file.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
World War, 1914-1918-Russia; Refugees; Russia. Armiia--Officers; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921; Russia--Emigration and immigration; Vrangel', Petr Nikolaevich, baron, 1878-1928.
Related Material
There are two additional Vrangel' collections in the Hoover Institution. One originates with General Baron Petr Nikolaevich Vrangel' and another with Baroness Maria D. Vrangel'.
Vrangel' collection, 1916-1929, Hoover Institution Archives
Baronessa Mariia Dmitrievna Vrangel' collection, 1915-1944, Hoover Institution Archives
Collection Contents
- Family file, 1908-2003.; 5 boxes (Box 1-5)
  Includes letters, service records, personal papers, articles, and obituaries relating to General Baron Petr Nikolaevich Vrangel'.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Family history, undated; Available on microfilm reel 1 (Folder 1: 1-2)
    Includes correspondence, astrological chart, the book Geschichte der Wrangel zur dänischen und Ordenszeit, and an edict of the Most Holy Synod of Russia (photocopy)
  - Petr Nikolaevich Vrangel' (1878-1928), 1908-2003
    - Children's drawing, undated; Available on microfilm reel 1 (Folder 1: 3)
    - Fairy tale and nursery rhymes, holograph (in Russian) by Petr Nikolaevich Vrangel', undated; Available on microfilm reel 1 (Folder 1: 4)
    - Service record, 1921 December 29; Available on microfilm reel 1 (Folder 1: 5)
    - Order of the day, 1916 January 27; Available on microfilm reel 1 (Folder 1: 6)
    - Correspondence
      - Ol'ga Mikhailovna Vrangel' (wife)
        - Pre-revolutionary period
          - 1908-1914, Available on microfilm reel 1 (Folder 1: 7-8)
          - 1914-1915, Available on microfilm reel 1 (Folder 1: 9)
          - 1914-1917, Available on microfilm reel 1 (Folder 1: 10)
          - 1915-1916, Available on microfilm reel 1 (Folder 1: 11)
        - Letters from the Army (after the Revolution), 1917.; Available on microfilm reel 1 (Folder 1: 12)
          Includes typescripts of the letters.
        - Civil War, 1919-1921; Available on microfilm reel 1 (Folder 1: 13)
        - Emigration, Available on microfilm reel 1
          - 1921-1928, Available on microfilm reel 1 (Folder 1: 14)
          - circa 1923, Available on microfilm reel 2 (Folder 1: 15)
          - 1923-1924, Available on microfilm reel 2 (Folder 1: 16)
          - 1926, Available on microfilm reel 2 (Folder 1: 17)
          - 1927, Available on microfilm reel 2 (Folder 2: 1)
          - 1927-1928, Available on microfilm reel 2 (Folder 2: 2-3)
      - Princess Mariia Vladimorovna, 1918-1928; Available on microfilm reel 2 (Folder 2: 4)
        Includes letters from Ol'ga Mikhailovna Vrangel'.
      - Boris Alekseevich regarding Russian Army in Constantinople, 1921 May 13; Available on microfilm reel 2 (Folder 2: 5)
    - Publications devoted to the last Russian Commander in Chief Lieutenant General Baron Petr Nikolaevich Vrangel', 1928-2003; Available on microfilm reel 2
      - Clippings, Available on microfilm reel 2
        - Bound, 1953-1978; Available on microfilm reel 2 (Folder 2: 6)
        - Loose, 1960-2003; Available on microfilm reel 2 (Folder 2: 7)
      - Newspapers and magazines, Available on microfilm reel 2
        - 1928, Available on microfilm reel 2 (Folder 2: 8)
        - 1929, Available on microfilm reel 2 (Folder 2: 9)
        - 1957, Available on microfilm reel 2 (Folder 2: 10)
        - 1971., Available on microfilm reel 2 (Folder 2: 11)
          Includes articles commemorating departure of the White Army from the Crimea.
        - 1979, Available on microfilm reel 2 (Folder 2: 12)
        - 1980, Available on microfilm reel 2 (Folder 2: 13)
        - 1981, Available on microfilm reel 2 (Folder 2: 14)
        - 1982, Available on microfilm reel 2 (Folder 2: 15)
        - 1993, Available on microfilm reel 2 (Folder 2: 16)
        - 1998, Available on microfilm reel 2 (Folder 2: 17)
      - Death anniversaries
        - Thirtieth, 1958; Available on microfilm reel 3 (Folder 2: 18)
        - Fortieth, 1968; Available on microfilm reel 3 (Folder 2: 19)
        - Fiftieth, 1978; Available on microfilm reel 3 (Folder 2: 20)
    - Obituaries and letters and telegrams of condolence on the death of Petr Nikolaevich Vrangel', 1928; Available on microfilm reel 3
      - General, Available on microfilm reel 3 (Folder 3: 1-2)
      - Volume 1 (Russian correspondents), Available on microfilm reel 3 (Folder 3: 3)
      - Volume 2 (Foreign correspondents), Available on microfilm reel 4 (Folder 3: 4)
      - Clippings (bound), Available on microfilm reel 4
        - Russian newspapers and magazines, 1928; Available on microfilm reel 4 (Folder 4: 1)
        - Rossiia, newspaper, 1928 May 5; Available on microfilm reel 10 (Folder 10: 1)
        - Foreign media, 1928; Available on microfilm reel 5 (Folder 4: 2)
      - Près de la tombe, musique de Th. Evsevsky, symphony devoted to General Baron Petr Nikolaevich Vrangel', 1928.; Available on microfilm reel 5 (Folder 4: 3)
        Includes marches of Kirasir and Sumy Regiments.
  - Ol'ga Mikhailovna Vrangel', wife of Petr Nikolaevich Vrangel' (1885-1968), 1908-1968; Available on microfilm reel 5 (Box 5)
    - Marriage certificate of Petr Vrangel' and O'lga Ivanenko, 1908 October 1; Available on microfilm reel 5 (Folder 5: 1)
    - Passports, 1918-1946; Available on microfilm reel 5 (Folder 5: 2)
    - Certificates and travel documents (as a wife of the Commander in Chief of the Russian Army), 1912-1919; Available on microfilm reel 5 (Folder 5: 3)
    - Correspondence, Available on microfilm reel 5
      - General, 1917-1923; Available on microfilm reel 5 (Folder 5: 4)
      - Family, undated.; Available on microfilm reel 5 (Folder 5: 5)
        Includes letters from her daughters Natal'ia and Elena.
    - Obituaries and letters of condolence, 1968; Available on microfilm reel 5 (Folder 5: 6)
    - "Fears for Finland Future," interview with Baroness Vrangel in the Detroit News, 1940 February 11; Available on microfilm reel 10 (Folder 10: 2)
  - Mariia Dmitrievna Vrangel', 1857-1944 (mother of Petr Nikolaevich Vrangel'). Letter to her granddaughter Natal'ia, undated; Available on microfilm reel 5 (Box 5: 7)
  - Alexis (Aleksei Petrovich) Vrangel', son of Petr Nikolaevich Vrangel' (1922-2005), 1922-2004; Available on microfilm reel 5
    - Personal documents and service papers, Available on microfilm reel 5
      - Birth certificate, 1922 July 7; Available on microfilm reel 5 (Folder 5: 8)
      - Mein Stammbuch Vrangel' family genealogy compiled by Alexis Vrangel', 1936.; Available on microfilm reel 5 (Folder 5: 9)
        In German.
      - Marriage certificates, Available on microfilm reel 5 (Folder 5: 10)
      - Certificate of naturalization, United States of America, 1948 December 13; Available on microfilm reel 5 (Folder 5: 11)
      - Diplomas, Available on microfilm reel 5 (Folder 5: 12)
      - Letter of recommendation, Headquarters, Continental Air Command, Mitchell Air Force Base, New York, 1955; Available on microfilm reel 5 (Folder 5: 13)
    - Correspondence, 1958-2004; Available on microfilm reel 5 (Folder 5: 14)
    - Publishing file, 1961-1987; Available on microfilm reel 5 (Folder 5: 15)
      Includes letter from A. Shcherbatov regarding the Smolensk GPU Archive.
- Photographs, 1912-1929.; 7 folders (Box 5)
  Prints depicting Petr Nikolaevich Vrangel' during the Russian Civil War and in exile. Many prints depict his burial in Belgrade, Yugoslavia.
  - Petr Nikolaevich Vrangel', undated.; 2 photographs; Available on microfilm reel 5 (Folder 5: 18)
  - Petr Nikolaevich Vrangel' as Horse Guards officer, Saint Petersburg, Russia, 1912; Available on microfilm reel 5 (Folder 5: 19)
  - Parade in Tsaritsyn (Southern Russia) with General Denikin, Civil War, 1919; Available on microfilm reel 5 (Folder 5: 19)
  - Petr Nikolaevich Vrangel' with his wife, Constantinople, 1921.; 2 prints; Available on microfilm reel 5 (Folder 5: 19)
  - Petr Nikolaevich Vrangel' with cadets in Yugoslavia, 1922.; 2 prints; Available on microfilm reel 5 (Folder 5: 19)
  - General Baron Petr Nikolaevich Vrangel' in Zemun, Yugoslavia, 1922 March 19.; 1 album; Available on microfilm reel 5 (Folder 5: 20)
  - Russian Army in the Balkans, 1922-1923.; 1 postcard album; Available on microfilm reel 5 (Folder 5: 21)
  - Russian Army in exile (everyday activities), 1925.; 1 album; Available on microfilm reel 6 (Folder 5: 22)
  - Petr Nikolaevich Vrangel', burial in Belgrade, Yugoslavia, 1929.; 29 prints; Available on microfilm reel 6 (Folder 5: 23)
  - Ninth Siberian Battalion, Ura-Tiub, 1870 August.; 1 print; Available on microfilm reel 10 (Folder 10: 3)
- Military archive, 1914; 4 boxes (Box 6-9)
  - Polki Imperatorgkoi konnitsy, bound manuscript, circa 1914.; Available on microfilm reel 6 (Folder 6: 1)
    Includes verses.
  - Polki Imperatorgkoi kavalerii, holograph lists, undated; Available on microfilm reel 6 (Folder 6: 2)
  - Shatilov, P. N., General, memoirs, undated. (Box 6-9)
    - Volumes 1-3, undated.; Available on microfilm reel 6 (Box 6: 3-5)
    - Volumes 4-6, undated.; Available on microfilm reels 7 and 8 (Box 7: 1-4)
    - Volumes 7-11, undated.; Available on microfilm reels 8 and 9 (Box 8: 1-5)
    - Volumes 12-13, undated.; Available on microfilm reel 9 (Box 9: 1-2)
      Includes content summary
  - Sbornik Rossiiskoi voennoi poezii, izdanie obshche-kadetskogo ob'edineniia, Paris, 1957; Available on microfilm reel 9 (Box 9: 3)
- Katkov family file, 1854-1910; 2 files; Available on microfilm reels 9 and 10 (Box 9)
  - Letters, memoranda, and essays by M. N. Katkov, copied by his daughter, N. M. Ivanenko, undated.; Available on microfilm reel 10 (Folder 9: 4)
    Bound manuscript
  - Correspondence relating to the Katkov family, 1849-1910; Available on microfilm reel 6 (Folder 6: 2)